Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Begging him to dine with them and meet [Charles] Prince de Deux Ponts, who has a proposition on the part of Bavaria concerning commercial relations with the United States. Often drinks his health with M. de Keralio. Thanking him for the four bottles of hock.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 21; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brancas, Marquis de
    Inquires at what hour he can see Franklin to speak to him about a young man in whom he is interested and who is at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 21; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Izard, Mrs. Ralph. Paris
    Request for a pass to America for her family and Miss Stead.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Maclntosh, -----. Paris
    Concerning certain parcels addressed to Dr. Franklin and others by Major [Samuel] White.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 22; A.L.S. 6p.; Duché, Jacob. Asylum, Lambeth
    Will abide by Franklin's kind advice and wait with patience to hear from his friends in Philadelphia; left there with the full knowledge and approbation of his congregation; encloses a copy of the address sent him by the Church-wardens and vestrymen of Christ's Church and st. Peter's in Philadelphia [2p.]; believes his friends will solicit the Government in favor of his return; has written [John] Dickinson, Robert Morris and Gen. Washington; thinks a word of recommendation from Franklin would carry great weight. His son, aged twenty, is a pupil of Benjamin West and bids fair to become a fine painter; other details about his family. Encloses copy of an extract of a letter he wrote to Francis Hopkinson [8 p.] defending his motives for leaving England and expressing a desire to return to America, in spite of his present comfortable position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Lameth, Charles-Malo-François, comte de. Paris
    Acknowledging the precious pledge of esteem with which America has honored him; in case of another war, hopes to find more opportunities of deserving so valued a reward.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 22; L.S. 1p.; Greissot ?, -----. Villeneuve
    Enclosing a memoir of Jaques Blanches [2p.] asking for his share of the prize-money during his cruise on the "south Carolina."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Hadenbrock, Jean. Bordeaux
    Thanking him for his two letters of recommendation; intends sailing shortly in the "Grand d'Estating".
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Strange, Isabella. London
    Thanks him for his care of her correspondence; begs that the enclosed may be forwarded; it contains the copy of a will by which her cousin Mrs. [James] Hunter [of Richmond, Va.], inherits some money by the death of her grandfather the Rev. Dr. Russell.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Cachard, chevalier de. Marseilles
    Begs him to answer a letter from a poor merchant of Marseilles, whose possession of a considerable sum in American paper money has contributed to his ruin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Corny, Dominique-Louis Ethis de
    Introducing Mr. D'Acosta, a gentleman of Nantes, who has some business to discuss relative to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Desire to know whether Capt. Coreil may expect his passport. Sends an account of money advanced to American prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Belletti, Dominique-François. Trieste
    Concerning his being made an American Consul. Desires an answer relative to the vessel he proposes sending to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 25; A.L.S. 6p.; Guinchard, François-Marie. Arpajon
    Electrical treatment of a paralytic, a little girl of two years, with the help of clever surgeon in his parish; results obtained; begs for Franklin's opinion and advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Davies, Mary Ann. Florence
    Anxious to hear concerning his health and happiness. Grief and trouble through which she and her sister have passed; their recent money loss; death of the Empress Maria Theresa who had always befriended them. Necessity of doing something for her support. Her facility in playing on the armonica; was the first and, she believes, the only successful public player on that instrument; suggests the possibility of being employed permanently by the Queen of France to play for her; begs Franklin's intercession for herself and also for her sister, who would sing in Italian operas or at the Queen's concerts; begs him not to instruct any other player on the armonica, or show them how to make one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Franklin expected all afternoon and greatly missed by the mistress of the house, her children, [Charles], Prince de Deux-Ponts and his humble servant; the Prince anxious to give Franklin the subjoined letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Brahm, François de. Collence
    On behalf of an anxious family, begs for some news of a beloved son and brother; the last heard from him was a letter written from Philadelphia the year before.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] April 27; L. 1p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Regretting her inability to give him a cup of tea on Monday; goes to the Italian comedy and then to Versailles for the rest of the week; urges him to dine with them the following week.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Madlin, -----. Paris
    Advising Dr. Franklin of an account due him by William Temple Franklin for repairs to a cabriolet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Boudinot, Elias. Philadelphia
    Recommending Col. [Matthias] Ogden of the New Jersey line; his distinguished conduct in the late war. In daily and anxious expectation of the definitive treaty; no official letters have arrived since February. The terms of peace give universal satisfaction except the article relative to English debts; thinks three or four years at least should be allowed for their payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Wright, Patience. London
    Had a long chat with Franklin's son; he looks well but old, and is very prudent; consequence of his being chosen by New Jersey. Is now in fashion at Court and can speak useful truths. The Parliament divided with regard to the loyalists and the justice of their claims on the King. Nothing will be settled till Franklin makes them a visit. The Prince of Wales called on them on Friday. Lord Dartmouth and others employ her son-in-law to paint their portraits. Major Labilliere has the Christian army almost ready; he calls himself a Christian soldier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 29; A.L.S. 4p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Introducing Mr. James Robertson. A description of his experiments in electricity. Unaccountable delay of M. Le Bègue de Presle in printing his manuscript; in case he is sick or dead, begs Fraklin to engage M. Le Roy to undertake the business. Question of Franklin's visit to Vienna; adulation he will meet with; will try and prevent its being burdensome. Desired by Count Lacy, Maréchal of thier armies, to ask Franklin whether the famous sculptor, M. Ceraqui of Rome, could be employed in America for making statues, busts and monuments, which will doubtless be erected to thier eminent men. Regrets the choice of Ministers made by the King of England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Introducing Col. Matthias Ogden of the New Jersey Brigade.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Brantsen, Gerard
    Sending Franklin a letter which arrived for him from Vienna. Acknowledging his gift of the medal, a precious monument of a great epoch.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Roberts, Thomas. Dunkirk
    Commanded several privateers under the American and French flags; account of his capture and imprisonment in England; obtained his liberty and returned to Dunkirk; out of employment and destitute of means; begs for a commission to sail under American colors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 30; L in 3d P. 1p.; Blome, Baron Otto von. Paris
    Sent Franklin's letter to the Baron de Rosencrone. Acknowledging the gift of the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 30; L.S. 2p.; Geay, François. Philadelphia
    Deserted from the French service about forty years before; spent two years in Holland, and since then has been a citizen in America; question of his inheriting a French estate; begs Franklin to obtain the necessary letters of pardon to enable him to enjoy this inheritance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 1; A.L.S. 1p.; La Houssaye, -----, vicomte de. Rennes
    As the Chief Treasurer of the War Department in the Province of Brittany, sent many millions to Boston; in consideration of his services, asks that he may receive a medal celebrating America's independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Garos, Louis-Julien. Fontenay-le-Comte
    Account of François Geay's desertion from the French army; has fallen heir to an estate which he may not inherit because of this; begs Franklin to obtain his pardon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Croust, -----, Cordier de. Laon
    His desire to emigrate to America with his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 [1784?] May 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel. Philadelphia
    Sends the petition [2p., dated March 12, 1784] presented to the Assembly of Pennsylvania, it being a joint request from the American Philosophical Society and the Library Company of Philadelphia for greater convenience in their accommodations; mentions certain lots on State House Square as most suitable for the design intended; opposition to this request; thinks a letter from Franklin arriving before the motion is made would have great influence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 4; L.S. 3p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Begging for letters of recommendation for Jacques Mazurié, who intends establishing a commercial house at Philadelphia. Apologizing for an indiscreet question he asked Franklin. Concerning certain French officers who were present at the defeat of Lord Cornwallis and who propose asking Franklin to present them with the medal; will dissuade them from this step if Franklin wishes it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Sending Franklin three hundred copies of the description of the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Benezet, Anthony. Philadelphia
    Sending him a petition from François Geay; does not doubt Franklin's kind interposition in the poor fellow's behalf. Sends him a small collection on the simplicity of the Christian religion, which is worthy of serious consideration; refers to certain events mentioned in those pages, especially to the killings of one hundred Christianized and friendly Indians by the whites. Pronounces a tirade against war. After teaching the youth of Philadelphia for nearly forty years, has obtained the office of teacher of the black children and others of that people; his opinion of the infamous traffic in slaves; intends publishing a paper on the evils of slavery; quotes the Abbé Paynal; strongly desires Franklin's return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Astruc, Daniel. Bordeaux
    Enclosing a bill [1p.] against the Sicur Grive of New England, who bought certain merchandise of him, and then left without paying; begs Franklin to find out his present whereabouts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Beyerlé de Fachevert, John Francis. Philadelphia
    Franklin's kindness in furnishing him with letters of introduction for America; emboldened by this to ask his influence with his uncle, Major-General de Beyerlé, to send him enough money to purchase a piece of land and the animals, implements etc., to work it; begs Franklin to represent to his uncle the disagreeable consequences which will result from his refusal; may draw a letter of exchange on Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 9; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Wilkinson, William and Miss Wilkinson [Margaret or May ?]. Paris
    Will do themselves the honor of dining with Dr. Franklin on the following Sunday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartwig, Sebastian. Gotha
    Wants a loan, which his brother in America will refund. Encloses letter for his brother.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Wilkinson, William. Paris
    Asking for letters of introduction for Mr. Philip Nicklin, an English gentleman, who intends establishing, in Philadelphia, a house in the linen trade in connection with that of Dickinson, Lloyd and Nicklin in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 10; L.S. 1p.; Artaud, Jean-Baptiste. Avignon
    Thinks Franklin will find in his writings an excuse for the request he now makes for a medal celebrating the independence of America; it will be cherished in his family as an heirloom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 10; L.S. 2p.; Pavola, Joachim-Marie de. Marseilles
    Concerning the desire expressed by M. Jerome Manfrin, a rich merchant of Venice, to entertain Franklin during his rumored visit to that city; charged with conveying this invitation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 11; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cologan, Mme de
    Regrets to be unable to dine with Franklin to-day. Sends him some bottles of wine from the Canary Islands produced on the estate of M. de Cologan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Ahax, -----, baronne d’. Paris
    Desiring a private interview with Frankllin as she is in need of his advice.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. His time so limited that appointments to see persons on their private affairs often prove inconvenient; begs la Baronne to state her affair in writing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 12; L. in 3d. P. 1p.; Boers, [Frederik Willem?]. Paris
    Always honored by Franklin's commands and ready to carry them out to the best of his abilities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Schmidt, C.F. Friderichsberg near Coppenhagen
    Asks questions relating to emigration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Proli, Pierre-Jean-Berchtold, comte de. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to give him a passport for his ship "La Capricieuse," and a letter of recommendation for her Captain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Sails for Boston by the first ship; business connected with Mrs. Mecom. Disappointment of Franklin's friends should he fail to visit England. If Franklin takes passage to Boston, begs that he will stay at his house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]? May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Lanoue, -----. Paris
    Is the inventor of a flying machine, which does not at all resemble Mr. Blanchard's; its construction will cost but ten louis; begs Franklin to defray this expense and enjoy with him the subsequent success.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 14; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Walterstorff, M de
    Returning the Constitutions of the United States; these laws, if executed with the same spirit of philosophy and sound policy which framed them, will insure constant happiness to the country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Falconer, Nathaniel. London
    Has just arrived from Philadelphia; if Franklin has any commands will be glad to execute them. Left Mr. and Mrs. [Richard] B(e)ach[e] well. Delighted at the report of Franklin's intended return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Gelatte, ------. Bouguenais
    Offers his services to America in his capaticy of surgeon; would like a position in some hospital or town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Ginette frères and Luc Laugier. Marseilles
    Hoping that Franklin will forward their interests in a certain affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 15; L.S. 2p.; The "Intendant of Lyons." Paris
    Recommending M. Dainval, a merchant of Lyons, as Agent for the United States in the latter city. Is recommended also by the Marquis de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Maillebois, comte de
    Reproaches himself for not personally acknowledging the medal sent him by Franklin. Asks for letters for recommendation for the bearer, M. de Banne, who is about to sail for America.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. Directing that he be given letters to Dr. [Samuel] Cooper, Gen. [Nathanael] Greene and Mr. [Robert R.] Livingston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Sieck, J.A.C. Berlin
    Wishes employment as Postmaster in the United States. Refers to secret information, in his possession, concerning the United States.
    (See LIX, 22 and 24, pp. 97 and 99.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Illens, ----- de. Marseilles
    Transcribes a copy of his letter of January 31st, 1783; begs Franklin to answer it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Ourry, Ann. Kinsale
    Feels sure that Franklin will serve her father's unfortunate family; encloses a line from Mr. Fagan, certifying to her distress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 16; A.L.S. 8p.; Denans, -----. La Seyne
    Concerning the two free ports in Europe to be accorded to the United States; one must be on the ocean and the other on the Mediterranean; difficulty of making a wise choice among so many applicants; strongly in favor of La Seyne in the Bay of Toulon for the Mediteranean sea-port; tremendous advantage of its situation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Sieck, J.A.C. Berlin
    Refers to letter of May 15. Asks for £12 travelling expenses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 17; A.L.S. 2 p.; Arle, P. Port-la-Vigne
    Writes on behalf of a friend, a surgeon who desires to pursue his calling in America in some assured position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Paillet, -----. Versailles
    Begs Franklin to help him to an occupation; his love of voyaging; difficulty of obtaining a place in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Francke, ----- de. Strasbourg
    Report that the United States intends having a quantity of cannon made France; offers to arrange the whole business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Berruyer, -----, chevalier de. Chateau de St. Fromond
    Account of his services in America; money he lost in these praiseworthy efforts; account of the whole affair, and the justice of his claims; begs Franklin to write to the French Ministers in his favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 19; L in 3d P. 1p.; Adams, John. Paris
    Several things requiring the deliberation of the American Ministers; proposes a meeting at the Hotel du Roi the next day at eleven.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 19; L.S. 3p.; Clairval, Duchesac and Fauché de. Paris
    Franklin's kindness in promising his protection for the establishment of a play-house in Philadelphia; report that many deputies from the United States are at present with Franklin; desires that his project may be placed before them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Walsh, James. Dunkirk
    His services in American navy; imprisoned in England and escaped; married in Bedford Country; his destitute condition; begs assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 20; A.L.S. 3P.; Herbigny, ----- Rutledge d'. Rheims
    Thanking him for his assistance in procuring her pension; the smallness of the sum does not impair her gratitude.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783?] May 20; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Walterstorff, ----- de
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 20; A.L.S. 2P.; Chabrit, Pierre. Paris
    Sending to the law giver of the New World the first volume concerning the laws of the great people of the Old World. 1
    1 [De la Monarchie Françaisc et de ses Lois.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Viny, John et al. London
    Takes this opportunity, by M. Du Chateau, to recall himself to Franklin's memory; begs for a few lines; has furnished M. Du Chateau with a set of wheels which will show his skill to be undiminished; encloses a list of his subscribers [1 p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Terrier, L. Marseilles
    Offering his services to America as a surgeon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Monteil, -----, chevalier de. Paris
    Acknowledging his civility; expects to bear witness to his many virtues in the places where he is going.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mosley, ----- and ----- Luï, Jr.[?]. Paris
    Will dine with Dr. Franklin on the 25th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 24; L.S. 1p.; Allen, John. Bordeaux
    Wrote on the 29th ult., requesting register for his brigantine; begs for a favorable answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Johonnot, Gabriel. Baltimore
    Begs Franklin to procure a passage for his son, recall him from Geneva, and direct his embarkation to Boston; the boy's grandfather looks for him with no small anxiety; gratitude for the kindness shown his son by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Acceptance of Franklin's invitation by the Comtesse de Forbach; will bring her children if possible; if not, their place will be filled by M. le Baron de Wish.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 263.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Introducing [William] Bingham; if Mrs. Bingham accompanies him, warns Franklin against showing her such attentions as may deprive them too long of her society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Guist, -----, baron de. Milan
    Congratulating Franklin on the independence of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Holland, Elizabeth, London
    Her husband, Thomas Holland, gave up his rank in the British army to fight for the Americans, and was killed during the war; left in a destitute condition with three children; begs Franklin to bring her case before Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Spener, Charles. Berlin
    His plan of publishing an American almanac in German, for the following year; among other things, it will contain a history of the Revolution and pictures of famous Americans; applies to Franklin for engravings of portraits, medals, uniforms, flags, etc; the histotical part of the almanac will be entrusted to Mr. Sprengel, Professor of history at the University of Halle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 26; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bandeira, ----- de Monteiro. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of the letters promised him as he leaves the next day for Lisbon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 26; L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Office of Finance
    Is to continue somewhat longer in his Office of Finance. Desires he would repeat his application for a loan in France, and hopes that, as the King's expenses are lessened, he may be able to comply with his gracious intention towards America; account of the distressed situation of America.
    (Copy. In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Maggi, Pietro. Milan
    Has distinguished himself at the University of Pavia; obliged through some family disgrace to leave Italy; begs Franklin's help in procuring him occupation in America.
    (In Itlaian.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 May 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Paleske, Charles. Humburg